Guide to the Pittsburgh Symphony Society Records, 1927-1964 AIS.1966.16
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Symphony Society Records
1927-1964
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Symphony Society
AIS.1966.16
14.75 Linear Feet (7 boxes; 21 oversized ledgers and scrapbooks)
The Pittsburgh Symphony Society was formed in 1927 to support the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra. This collection consists of organizational records, committee activities, contracts, active and inactive Society membership cards, brochures, advertisements, financial records and ledgers, scrapbooks, and newspaper clippings.
History
The Pittsburgh Symphony Society emanated from the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra to support, encourage, and promote further interest in the arts. The Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra was originally formed in 1895 and disbanded due to financial difficulties in 1910. It was 1926 before the orchestra was reestablished with its members rehearsing for no fee and each musician contributed money to make a new season in 1927 possible. The Pittsburgh Symphony Society was formed in 1927 to administer the daily tasks associated with running a symphony. The Society raised funds in order to maintain an orchestra by actively soliciting corporate and individual members, running the box office, and careful accounting. The Society was also responsible for arranging contracts between musicians and conductors, along with program advertisers. The Pittsburgh Symphony Society sought to raise the profile of the symphony promoting performances in local publications, through advertisements and announcements. In order to instill a life-long appreciation of music, the Society organized frequent Young People's Concerts for local school children. The Pittsburgh Symphony Society's primary goal was to promote and financially support the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra. It achieved world wide renown and recognition, often appearing in national and international publications to great acclaim.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection contains financial records, organization records, contracts, operational material on the Pittsburgh Symphony and active and inactive Society membership cards, financial campaign material, scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, committee activities, advertisements, and memorabilia.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh Symphony Society Records, 1927-1964, AIS.1966.16, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
Series I. Administrative Files, 1927-1959
Series II. Press Files, 1928-1955
Series III. Financial Files, 1934-1964
Series IV. Membership Files, 1927-1958
Series V. Scrapbooks, 1943-1956
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Edwards on September 9, 1966.
Related Material
American Federation of Musicians, Local 60-471 Records, 1906-1996, AIS.1997.41, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Pittsburgh Chamber Music Society Records, 1961-2009, AIS.1998.51, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Penn Theater, Pittsburgh, Pa., Records, 1927-1964, AIS.1968.06, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Musical groups -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Conductors (Musicians); Music; Societies; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social life and customs; Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra; Pittsburgh Opera (Pa.); American Federation of Musicians. Local 60 (Pittsburgh, Pa); Pittsburgh Symphony Society; Reiner, Fritz
- Administrative Files, 1927-1959; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The Administrative Files series contains information on the daily administration of the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra by the Pittsburgh Symphony Society. Included in this series are documents on organizing special concerts for local school children, contracts with various musicians, along with programs, orchestra tour schedules, and tickets. Also included in this series is correspondence and notes from the Board of Directors, President, Vice President, Secretary, and Manager of the Pittsburgh Symphony Society. This Administrative Files series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Executive Board Remarks, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Executive Board of the Pittsburgh Symphony Society By-Laws, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Executive Board Memos, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reports to the Board of Directors and Call for Meetings, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Petition to the Trustees of the Falk Foundation, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Contract between Pittsburgh Symphony and American Federation of Musicians, Local 60, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Contracts Soloists and Conductors, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Contract with Pittsburgh Opera Society, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Contracts with American Federation of Musicians, Local 60, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Contracts with Soloists, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Contracts with Program Advertisers, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Contracts with Program Advertisers, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Contracts with Soloists, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Contracts with Program Advertisers, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Conductor's Symposium, Notes and Photographs, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Floor plans for Proposed Music Hall, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Manager, Edward Specter, 1936-1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Manager, William McKelvy Martin, Incoming Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Manager, John S. Edward, Outgoing Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Performance Program Notes for Joan of Arc, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pittsburgh Symphony Society Annual Meeting, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pittsburgh Junior Symphony Audition Cards, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pittsburgh Junior Symphony, 1953,1956 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Pittsburgh Symphony Society Campaign Letterhead, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Pittsburgh Symphony Society Envelope Letterhead, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Pittsburgh Symphony Society Luncheon, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Pittsburgh Symphony Society Ticket Stubs, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Pittsburgh Symphony Tour Schedule, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - President, Mrs. William Maclay Hall, Correspondence, 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - President, Charles Denby, Notes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - President, Charles Denby, Report to the Board of Directors, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - President, Charles Denby, Outgoing Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Programs, 1927-1954 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Programs, Concerts for High School Students, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Program, Railroad Night at the Symphony, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Programs, Pittsburgh Orchestra Association Concert, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Secretary, Richard J. Rauh, Correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Secretary Richard J. Rauh, Notes and Newspaper Clippings, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Vice-President, E.T. Weir, Incoming Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Vice-President, E.T. Weir, Outgoing Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Young People's Concert, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Young People's Concerts, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Young People's Concerts, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Young People's Concerts, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Young People's Concerts Questionnaire, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Young People's Concert Seating Arrangement, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Young People's Concerts Promotional Material, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Young People's Concerts Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Press Files, 1928-1955; II.
  The Press Files series contains material that publicized performances of the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra. Included in this series are numerous newspaper clippings from local and national publications that show the popularity and renown of the symphony. The Press Files series also feature advertisement and announcements of symphony concerts. Of particular interest are a brief biography written by the Society on renowned conductor Fritz Reiner and press releases from Columbia Music on recording released of Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra performances. This series is arranged by year.
  - Symphony Concert Flyers, 1928-1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Concert Flyer, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings on Symphony Guest Artists, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Symphony Concert Flyers, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Symphony Advertisements, 1940-1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Symphony Newspaper Clippings and Advertisements, 1941-1943 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Fritz Reiner Biography and Newspaper Clippings, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Symphony Press Releases, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Symphony Concert Announcements, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Press Releases for the Performance of Handel's Messiah, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - High School Concerts Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Press Releases, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Financial Files, 1934-1964; III.
  This series chronicles the financial accounting of maintaining the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra. The Financial Files series includes information on various fundraising campaigns, contributions pledged, box office statements, and expenditure reports. This series also includes twelve oversized financial ledgers detailing cash receipts, disbursements, accounts, and payroll. The Financial Files series is arranged by year.
  - Symphony Fundraising Campaign Dinner Program, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Bank Deposit Books, 1934-1939 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Symphony Budget, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Symphony Fundraising Campaign Material, 1939, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Orchestra Tours Expenses, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Symphony Fundraising Campaign Worker's Kit, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Orchestra Tours Expenses, 1950-1955 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Orchestra Fundraising Campaign, 1950-1951, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Box Office Statements, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Symphony Fundraising Campaign Information, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Comparative Operating Results, 1952-1957 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Box Office Statements, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Corporate Sponsors Gifts, 1952-1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Box Office Statements, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Weekly Summary Expenditure Reports, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Disbursement Statements, May to December, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Disbursement Statements, January to June, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Disbursement Statements, July to December, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Weekly Summary Expenditure Reports, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Disbursement Statements, January to June, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Disbursement Statements, July to December, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Deficit, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Contributions Pledged, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Budget, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Weekly Summary Expenditure Reports, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Disbursement Statements, January to June, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Disbursement Statements, July to December, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Weekly Summary Expenditure Reports, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Disbursement Statements, January to June, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Disbursement Statements, July to December, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Weekly Summary Expenditure Reports, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Disbursement Statements, January to June, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Disbursement Statements, July to December, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Cash Disbursements, June 1927- February, 1934 (Oversize Ledger 1)
  - Cash Receipts, June 1927- February 1944 (Oversize Ledger 2)
  - Account Book, March 1926- October 1926 (Oversize Ledger 3)
  - Account Book, June 1927- May 1934 (Oversize Ledger 4)
  - Account Book, June 1927- May 1939 (Oversize Ledger 5)
  - Account Book, May 1939- December 1946 (Oversize Ledger 6)
  - Cash Receipts, February 1944- June 1956 (Oversize Ledger 7)
  - Cash Disbursements, March 1944- June 1956 (Oversize Ledger 8)
  - Account Book, December 1946- April 1952 (Oversize Ledger 9)
  - Account Book, April 1952- January 1957 (Oversize Ledger 10)
  - Payroll Book, 1962-1963 (Oversize Ledger 11)
  - Check Register, 1962-1964 (Oversize Ledger 12)
- Membership Files, 1927-1958; IV.
  The Membership Files series details the various membership campaigns and drives lead by the Pittsburgh Symphony Society. Included in this series are index cards of season subscribers and correspondence with corporate sponsors, events planned and coordinated by the Pittsburgh Symphony Society Womem's Association. This series is arranged by year.
  - Membership Campaign (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 4)
  - Membership Cards, 1927-1929 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence to Members (Form Letter), 1927-1928, 1930 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 6)
  - Women's Association Meeting Minutes, 1937 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 7)
  - Membership Campaign Drive, 1937 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 8)
  - Women's Association Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 9)
  - Women's Association Form Letters, 1938-1939, 1954-1955 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 10)
  - Women's Association Reply Cards, 1939, 1954-1955 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 12)
  - Membership Campaign, 1943-1944 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 12)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee List of Organizations, 1950 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 13)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Prospective Donors, 1950-1951 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 14)
  - Women's Association, Board of Directors Nominations, 1951 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 15)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Draft of Proposed Letters, 1951-1952, 1955 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 16)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Memos and Charts, 1952 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 17)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence, 1952 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 18)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Luncheon, 1952 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 19)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Lists of Amount Donated by Companies "A-D", 1952-1953 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 20)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Reports, 1952-1954 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 21)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Allegheny Ludlum Steel Corporation, 1952-1953 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 22)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "A-C", 1952-1956 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 23)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "D-E", 1952-1956 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 24)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "F-G", 1952-1956 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 25)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "H-J", 1952-1956 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 26)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "K-Mel", 1952-1956 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 27)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "Mi-N", 1952-1956 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 28)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "P", 1952-1956 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 29)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "P", 1952-1956 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 30)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "P-R", 1952-1956 (Oversize Ledger 12, Folder 31)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "S-U", 1952-1956 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence with Companies "W", 1952-1956 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Women's Association Correspondence, 1952, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Women's Association Membership List, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Women's Association Membership List, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Men's Committee Files, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Women's Association Symphony Ball Committee Notes, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Women's Association Symphony Ball Committee Notes, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Women's Association Membership List by School Zones, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Membership Campaign Drive, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Notes, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Committee Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Women's Committee Membership List, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Former Season Subscribers Cards, A-P, 1953-1958 (Box 8)
  - Former Season Subscribers Cards, R-Z, 1953-1958 (Box 9)
  - Corporate and Individual Contributors Cards, 1957 (Box 10)
  - Individual Contributors Cards, 1957 (Box 11)
  - Individual Contributors Cards, 1957 (Box 12)
  - Individual Contributors Cards, 1958 (Box 13)
  - Individual Contributors Cards, 1958 (Box 14)
- Scrapbooks, 1943-1956; V.
  This series features nine oversized scrapbooks of Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra performances and Pittsburgh Symphony Society activities. The scrapbooks are largely comprised of newspaper clippings and are arranged by date. The scrapbooks chronicling the activities of the Pittsburgh Symphony Society consist of form letter sent to member and memorabilia such as ticket stubs and pledge forms. The Scrapbook series is arranged by year.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1943-1944 (Oversize Scrapbook 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1944-1945 (Oversize Scrapbook 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1945-1946 (Oversize Scrapbook 3)
  - Fundraising Campaign, 1947-1948 (Oversize Scrapbook 4)
  - Form Letters to Members, 1948-1949 (Oversize Scrapbook 5)
  - Fundraising Campaign Forms, 1947-1948 (Oversize Scrapbook 6)
  - Form Letters to Members, 1948-1949 (Oversize Scrapbook 7)
  - Fundraising Campaign Forms, 1950-1952 (Oversize Scrapbook 8)
  - Newspaper Advertisements, 1953 (Oversize Scrapbook 9)